Meteorology Collection 1748-1822 Mss.551.5.M56
American Philosophical Society
Meteorology Collection
1748-1822
Mss.551.5.M56
American Philosophical Society
30.0 Volume(s)
Featuring the work of at least ten different authors, this collection includes several, unrelated meteorological observations from the mid-18th Century to the early 19th Century. While the majority of these records depict weather patterns in Philadelphia, there are also descriptions for Delaware, New England, London, and South America among others.
Various
Early American History Note
This collection contains a group of metrological observations made between the 1750-1800. The data was compiled at different locations and by different people. There are fifteen volumes kept by a member of the Pemberton family in the collection. These contain weather data for Philadelphia from the colonial and revolutionary era. There are also observations from England and elsewhere. Some of the data includes graphs and other detailed information.
Existence and Location of Copies note
Collection also available on microfilm (Film 1467, Reel 1).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by the authors and others, various dates.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains miscellaneous and unrelated meteorological observations from the mid-18th Century to the early 19th Century profiling locations as diverse as Philadelphia, South America, and London. The majority of the records contain daily charts noting the prominent weather indicators, some of which include remarks by the respective authors.
Adair, William; Curson, Samuel; Dunbar, William, 1749-1810; Haines, Reuben, 1786-1831; Hazard, Samuel, 1784-1870; Legaux, Peter,1748-1827.; Madison, James, 1751-1836; Pemberton, Phineas; Reichel, Charles Gotthold, 1751-1825; Williams, Samuel, 1743-1817; Meteorological Data; Meteorology - Delaware - Observations; Meteorology - New England - Observations; Meteorology - Observations; Meteorology - Pennsylvania; Meteorology - South America - Observations; Science and Technology; Weather
- Meteorology Collection, 1748-1822; ca. 30 items
  - Meteorological observations taken in and around Philadelphia, 1748-1776; I; 15 notebooks; Pemberton, Phineas
    Scope and Contents note
    D. 15 notebooks. Various sizes. (see Meteorological material, No. I.) Abstracted and printed in APS Trans., n.s., vol. VI, 395ff. Presented by James Pemberton; 1791. Cf. Minutes. 1. Aug.-Nov.1748:Dec.4,1748-Sept.30,1749. 2. Jan.1758-Feb.1760. 3. Jan.1767-April 1768: Jan.-Aug.28,1769: April-Nov.1770. 4. Jan.1768-Dec.1769. 5. Jan.-Dec.1770. 6. Dec.1770-Feb.1771: Dec.1770-July 24, 1772. 7. Jan.1771-Dec.1772. 8. Jan.-April 25, 1772: July 25-Oct.31, 1772.
  - Meteorological journals, 1758, 1767, 1768; II; Pemberton, Phineas
    D. 34 leaves. Various sizes. This seems to have been abstracted from the Meteorological observations...No.I of this group. Presented by James Pemberton; 1791. Cf.Minutes.
  - 1749-1778, III; Pemberton, Phineas
    - Account of barometer and thermometer at Bridgewater, England and Philadelphia, 1767-1768
    - Meteorological observations, taken at London, England (extracts), 1751-1761
    - Meteorological observations, taken at Maryland, 1753-1754
    - Meteorological observations, unidentified location, 1749, 1766-1767
    - Meteorological observations, taken at Philadelphia, 1770, 1774, 1777-1778
  - Meteorological observations, taken at Philadelphia, 1768; IV
  - The highest and lowest stations of the barometer and thermometer in London, 1771; V
  - Meteorological observations taken in New England, and account of a hurricane in New England, 1771, 1773; VI; Williams, Samuel
  - Meteorological observations at Lewes, DE., 1773-1775; VII; Adair, William
  - Tables of meteorological observations taken at Philadelphia, 1773-1777; VIII
  - Meteorological observations, taken at Nazareth, PA., 1787-1790; IX; Reichel, Charles Gotthold, 1751-1825
  - Meteorological observations, 1798-1802; X; Madison, James, 1751-1836
  - Meteorological observations, sent to John Vaughan, Natchez, 1803; XI; Dunbar, William, 1749-1810
  - Observations on the warmth of the sea water, etc. from Smyrna to Philadelphia, 1815; XII; Hazard, Samuel
  - Barometrical observations made in South America, [1817]; XIII; Curson, Samuel
  - Meteorological observations made at Spring Mill, PA, 1820-1821; XIV; Legaux, Peter
  - Meteorological observations made at Germantown, PA, 1820-1821; XV; Haines, Reuben
  - Remarks on meteorological observations, [ca. 1822]; XVI